<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony to the free and universal love of God in Jesus Christ to the sons of men in true love sent forth (more especially) to the inhabitants of Colchester and parts adjacent, for them to read over, and weigh with due and serious consideration, in the blessed fear of the Lord / by Thomas Bayle.</title>
            <author>Bayle, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11687565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11687565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 12:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony to the free and universal love of God in Jesus Christ to the sons of men in true love sent forth (more especially) to the inhabitants of Colchester and parts adjacent, for them to read over, and weigh with due and serious consideration, in the blessed fear of the Lord / by Thomas Bayle.</title>
                  <author>Bayle, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48168:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48168:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY TO THE FREE and UNIVERSAL LOVE of GOD IN <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> TO THE SONS of MEN: IN True Love ſent forth (more eſpecially) to the Inhabitants of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> and Parts adjacent; For them to read over, and weigh with due and ſerious Conſideration, in the bleſſed Fear of the LORD.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS BAYLE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hear Counſel, and receive Inſtruction, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be Wiſe in thy latter end.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48168:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48168:2"/>
            <p>THe Univerſal Love and free Grace of God to man kind, is again, (after a ſad and deplorable night of darkneſs) revealed and ſhewed unto thouſands, who have waited upon him in his holy Light, and Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſtation in their hearts and conſciences; and teſtified of, and born witneſs unto, in this our age and generation; for to enjoy which, what ſighing, what breathing for, and ſoul-traveling after, (in a holy hunger and thirſt, in deep exerciſe and travel of Spirit, in a holy faith and fear in the Lord) hath there been by many in former dayes and times, ſome yet living are able to give ſome teſtimony thereof: And this happy and bleſſed appearance of the Lord, to the call and reſtitution of mankind, to this his great kindneſs in Jeſus Chriſt, hath been ſounded forth in this place and parts; and that truly I may ſay, according to the Nature of it, which is free, and univerſal, and plentious, from the God and Father of it; and that very largly, with clearneſs and certainty, by his Servants, his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers and Miniſters, who here in this Town and County have laboured, for ſeveral years by paſt, both by word and writing: And the Lord hath given them fervencie of Spirit, zeal and courage, and alſo utterance in judgment and underſtanding, that ſinners might be converted unto him, and people come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to partake of that heavenly bleſſed life (which in the true light which now ſhines is made manifeſt) which the Saints and people of the Lord partaked of in the primitive times; and notwithſtanding this certain and infallible teſtimony, which hath been held forth in this place for theſe 20 years paſt, in kindneſs, tenderneſs, and love unfeigned, with freeneſs, to bring Souls home to the Lord, yet what darkneſs, ſecurity, and inſenſibility of heart and mind is there remaining in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48168:3"/> Conſciences and Spirits of the generality of you, as if there were no ſuch thing as Religion in truth and righteouſneſs to be minded, as if the Lord God had forſaken the habitable parts of the earth for man to live in the perverſe wayes of his own heart, and as if you had outlived that belief, which formerly was as a ſtanding Principle or Faith in peoples minds, of comeing to Judgment for the deeds done in the body, both the quick and the dead, the good and the bad (as the Scriptures teſtifie of) and that there is no ſuch thing to be as puniſhment unto the evil doer, tribulation, anguiſh and pain upon every ſoul that doth evil; nor reward of life eternal to them that do well. And this great evil (which is falſe hearts, eaſe and ſecurity in the fleſh) aboundeth very much amongſt you, even in and amongſt you my Neighbours, Townſmen and Acquaintance; and the conſideration thereof with grief and ſorrow of heart have I ſeriouſly weighed within my ſelf; and certainly can conclude nothing but a ſad and woful diſtruction from God Almighty, to be rewarded in flames of Fire from Heaven, into the boſoms of all ſuch as perſevere therein, until their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence, and be no more ſeen.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is a warning and charge unto you, into whoſe hands it may come, that you break off your ſins by time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repentance, and ſeek the Lord whilſt he may be found, and that in diſcharge of my Conſcience in the ſight of God, that the Teſtimony of the truth of our God may be kept up over the heads of all diſobedient gainſayers; and that that holy heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Principle, the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, in the Conſciences of all people, may have its place and due Authority in your hearts and lives, to the eternal Honour and Praiſe of ſo gratious and bountiful a giver; and to your bleſſedneſs and great felicity here in this life, and hereafter, when time with you ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>And God Almighty (the ſercher of our hearts) knows to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48168:3"/> whoſe righteous, eternal, and everlaſting Judgment, we ſhall all ſhortly ſtand, and for ever be concluded, that my end and intent herein is Gods glory and your ſalvation; this is my ſole and alone end and intent in this matter: And therefore bear with me a little in patience and quietneſs of your Spirits; and let not your hearts be like a boyling pot, becauſe I write unto you whom men diſpiſe, and am by Scorns called a <hi>Quaker;</hi> for be it known unto you, that if ſo you entertain my lines, and that innocent love which draws my heart in gentleneſs to viſit you, that you will be left in the hardneſs of your hearts the more to fill up the meaſure of your iniquity, that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may come upon you for all your evil deeds.</p>
            <p>And now concerning what I have to write, or chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend hereby, I ſhall write it as to two ſorts of men, or as in two ſtates and conditions, although they have different branches, yet ſpringing from one and the ſelf ſame root of evil, and not all ſinners according to one ſimilitude; and theſe I call Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and Profeſſor: And by Prophane I intend ſuch as make not a Profeſſion of Godlineſs, no more indeed, than thoſe that never heard of ſuch a thing, or as men without God in the world, as ſuch there are amongſt you, their lives teſtifie unto me herein; and are ſuch as live in wildneſs, ignorance, diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and confuſion; and cry, <hi>tuſh, who ſeeth?</hi> ſuch, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are given way unto, which are not civil, but rude: And this ought not to be, and it is time for ſuch, not to walk as in the dayes that are paſt, wherein fear that is holy, humility, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety and chaſtity were ſet at nought, for to poſſeſs and live in bad things, as lying, ſtealing, whoredome, wrath, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, ſwearing, and many wicked things more; which is a ſhame to any people, &amp; a burthen to the Creation of God, vexing the juſt and the righteous: And oh you untoward people, the ſound of theſe things, &amp; the evil effects thereof, how do I and many more paſs through the ſtreets and lanes, with the nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48168:4"/> ſmell and burthen of them falling upon us, for which we cannot but cry unto the Lord our God, under the heavy oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of; And for theſe things, the cryes aſcend up from the innocent ſouls againſt you, and the Lord is weary of iniquity, and would rid his Adverſary out of his way, and deſtroy him by the brightneſs of his coming, who worketh great evil in you, great ſin and tranſgreſſion againſt God, and againſt your own ſouls; and I ask you, what good doth your drunkenneſs or your ſwearing do you, or any other of thoſe evils which you accuſtome your ſelves unto? I am ſure you are deprived thereby of comfort, peace, and content here; and which is more, if not repented of, and that your repentance be before it be too late, will certainly end in your ruine and deſtruction for ever more.</p>
            <p>And therefore repent, repent of theſe your abominations, and live no longer in the luſts of your own evil hearts, but be ye conſiderate of your wayes and doings, of the tendency and end of them; for you are not wholly wrapt up in ignorance, the knowledge of ſin and evil (in ſome meaſure) you have enough to condemn you, if you repent not, if you put not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the evil of your doings, and learn ſoberneſs, juſtneſs, truth, and thoſe things which the Lord requires of you: for <hi>I have ſhewed thee, O man</hi> (ſaith the Lords Prophet) <hi>what the Lord requires of thee:</hi> and the Lords Prophet, (which he hath raiſed up) ſaith the ſame to you now; this knowledge and underſtanding (as I ſaid) in ſome meaſure you have; for you your ſelves know, you ſhould not ſwear, nor lye, nor ſteal, nor be drunk, nor violent (as lately ſome to their ſhame ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves) and where will you hide you? and what cloak will you take upon you (for Chriſt Jeſus the Judge is come) to cover you from his all-ſeeing eye, from whom in his light you have ſeen theſe things to be evil, to be bad, to be againſt him, and that you cannot ſtand by them, but are condemned
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48168:4"/> in your ſelves for them, and cry out, <hi>God forgive me, I ſhould not ſwear, or be drunk,</hi> or the like: but why then do you? are you altogether ignorant, that they that know their Maſters will and doth it not, are worthy to be beaten with many ſtripes? no not ignorant wholly, or altogether, for if ſo, then no cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for forgiveneſs would proceed from you; for where there is no Law, there is no tranſgreſſion; but it ſeems here is Law with you, and Tranſgreſſion with you; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you cry out to the Lord (whom you know you have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt) for forgiveneſs: ſo this you well know, and are not ignorant of.</p>
            <p>And thus you lye in great deſolation, and take ye heed, leſt it prove a deſolation for ever, and that your ſcattered broken ſtate you never witneſs the true Shepheards Crook to pull you out of it into that holy power which would (if you would ſubmit thereto) keep and preſerve you from that ſpirit of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ignorance and profaneneſs which now you are poſſeſs'd and ſo fill'd with, and overcome by, as that no eſcape or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance is by you known or ſought after, but he the evil one, which hath ruled in your members, in a ſad and woful night of tranſgreſſion, ſtill reigns and rules, as if you were made for his ſervice, and he as of right the juſt Lord and Ruler over you.</p>
            <p>Now you may underſtand that he that made you, made you for another purpoſe, and for another end, as that which ſhould be profitable unto you, and of great advantage (as namely, a Crown of Glory upon your heads, and that is that you ſhould ſerve him that made you, which is reaſonable, even that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bright and holy ſpirit of Wiſdome and power which formed you, and gave you being, and underſtanding, and knowledge beyond the Beaſts of the field, or the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent earthly Creatures and Bodies which you ſee moving upon the face of the Earth; and that ſervice which he expects from (accepts, and receives of) his Creatures, Man and Woman,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48168:5"/> is performed in and by a pure, holy, contrite, humble heart and ſpirit, and that it may be the fruit and product thereof, and not that which ſprings from a corrupted heart and root; and to that end, the Lord God hath beſtowed upon mankind univerſally (without reſpect to perſons) a meaſure of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and purity, which is of his own nature and purity, and doth proceed from him the Father of Lights, to gather man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain out of the ſtate of Darkneſs and death (where you are who walk in the luſts of the fleſh) into a ſtate of glory, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed ſtate, where all things are become new, clear and pure, to walk in the Light thereof, and glorious ſhinings in their hearts: And to this largely teſtifie the holy Scriptures, which I doubt not but ſome of you at ſome time or other have read ſomewhat of; wherein it's ſaid, That the grace of God which brings Salvation, hath appeared to all men, (if to all men, then to you) teaching us (who were they) they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in it and obeyed it, to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and it would do the ſame for you, and teach you as well as they, to live ſoberly and righteouſly in this preſent evil world, if you would bring your deeds to it, if you loved not darkneſs rather than light, if you would bow down in heart and conſcience in obedience and full ſubmiſſion to it; for it's work, and the very end of its being given (by the good giver of it) is to reprove, convince, inſtruct, guide and rule in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; and therein is it to be found and enjoyed, and the benefit that comes thereby, and not where you are in diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, gainſaying, and rebellion; for never any enjoyed it, or its teachings and leadings in ſuch a ſtate (although it knocks often, and calls to forſake death) but by ſubmiſſion to its pure holy teachings and requirings: and this is the Lords Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Angel of his holy Power, by which he calls unto man to hearken unto him, (to forſake death and live) that ſo to him doth call to return: And this voice, it's ſaid is behind
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48168:5"/> man, who is gone forth from it, (through the ſubtilty of that Serpent, who at firſt did, and ſtill doth deceive man, through mans hearkening unto him) calling upon him to go back a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain, and to go home to the Fathers houſe, and not to go forth, for no teacher is like unto him, as all who have come to his teaching, in this age, and in all ages paſt, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly born witneſs.</p>
            <p>But now you muſt be willing and obedient, if you would enjoy this innocent life, this Pearl of great price, this hope of Glory, than which, there is none beſides; you muſt receive it according to the Counſel of his own will: his Teſtimony is, I am come, not to ſend Peace on the earth, but a Sword; Fallen man cannot put forth his own hand to take of the Tree of Life and live, for there is a Sword, a flaming Sword put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of Cherubims, which turns every way, to keep him from it; of this you may have read: Thus was <hi>Adam</hi> in his tranſgreſſion ſtopt; and be you aſſured this Sword is not taken down, but ſtill turneth againſt you: I believe many of you at times feell the turning, or ſhaking of it againſt you; which makes you to fear, to tremble, to be afraid; and ſome to feel ſuch horrour, torment, and perplexity of ſpirit within you, when the thoughts or conſideration of death comes neer you, and who in your weakneſs of body, on your ſick beds cry out, <hi>O that the Lord would ſpare me this time, I would take warning, and become a new Creature, and live a more holy, ſelf-denying life than ever I did;</hi> and thus oft times the flamingneſs of it, and the ſharpneſs of it comes neer you, yea very neer you, even into your boſoms; but the way to get to the tree of life is not by a few falſe words and promiſes, utter'd on a ſick or dying bed, from an impenitent deceitful heart, which being in torment would have ſome cool water poured upon it: for I have ſometime known, when ſome ſuch have been ſpared, (and let theſe my words enter into your hearts conſideration,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48168:6"/> who are concerned herein) they have ſoon forgot God that ſmot them, and have returned with more greedineſs to that evil converſation, for which the juſt hand of God was lifted up in ſmart rebuke againſt them: therefore take heed to watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your wayes and doings, whilſt you have time: but this is the way, O Man and Woman, to this tree of life ſpoken of; return, return from the evil of your wayes and doings, and kiſs the Son, (that is to ſay) embrace him, hearken diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all bowedneſs of Spirit and humility of Soul upon this his inſhining ingr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed word, which is able alone to ſave your ſouls, and none other, nor nothing elſe; and here the ſoul that ſinneth muſt dye, and the judgment muſt be executed, and the flaming Sword have its place, and do its work, which is quick and ſharp, and divideth between joynts and marrow, ſoul and ſpirit, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart: can any thing come more neer to a man? feel ye this, have ye felt, or do ye feel this ſharpneſs, this quickneſs, (for it is to be felt) this dividing Sword of the Lord; which divides between a man and his lovers, and know your ſelves to be redeemed from that Spirit of tranſgreſſion which hath ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in your hearts, and yet does and has the dominion there, and know the Adverſary is deſtroyed by the brightneſs of his comeing, who comes to finiſh tranſgreſſion, and to make an end of ſin: It's time for you this to learn and know, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſhall you be, if now you come forth to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty, and keep not back your luſts, pleaſures, nor ſinful ſports and paſs-times, but deny your ſelves in thoſe things, and be willing and obedient, take the yoak of Chriſt upon you, and learn of him, who ſaith, hold that faſt which thou haſt, that you may eat the good of the good Land, the promiſed Land of Reſt to your ſouls, which flows with Milk and Honey: but as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, could not go on, in hope to poſſeſs the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but by paſſing from <hi>Egypt,</hi> through
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48168:6"/> the Red Sea, and a vaſt and weary Wilderneſs, wherein great exerciſes, tryals and ſorrows were, no more can ye inherit ſubſtance (the inheritance of the Saints in Light) and poſſeſs that peace, which the world can neither give nor take away, but by taking up the dayly Croſs, and following him, who ſaid unto the woman that asked him to have her two Sons to ſit, the one at his right hand, and the other at his left hand in his Kingdom: Can ye be Baptized with that Baptiſm that I ſhall be Baptized with? can ye drink of that Cup that I ſhall drink of? are you willing to ſuffer with him, and to be made like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, who was a man of ſorrow, even like unto his death, and to bear about in your bodies the dying of the Lord Jeſus, that ſo through the dying, and the death, you may come to know life, and the quicknings of it, and its virtue and holy opperation, to faſhion and mould you, to fit and prepare you for that Kingdom, for that Crown and weight of Glory, which is laid up in ſtore for all them that believe in Jeſus Chriſt, and follow him through the Regeneration: for through the being made in fellowſhip with him in his ſufferings, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed unto life by that eternal Spirit which raiſed up Jeſus from the dead, thou mayeſt reign with him in his Glory, in his bleſſedneſs, and eternal life world without end.</p>
            <p>But ye my Neighbours and Acquaintance, I have often ſeen and taken notice of a Spirit and Life in you altogether contrary hereunto, as being diſorderly, a ſcoffing mocking Spirit, of <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> nature abounding amongſt you, againſt the Spirit of the Lord, and its teachings, and movings, againſt the holy Light of Jeſus Chriſt within, and the Profeſſors and Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of it, which hath and doth tend greatly to the grief and burthen of Gods holy Spirit, which is teaching; and if you have not the Spirit of Chriſt, you are none of his; and this your unchriſtian carriage and behaviour the Lord will require it into your boſoms, in the day wherein he will enter into
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48168:7"/> Judgment with you, and then it will be unutterable ſad for you; and then you will find your ſelves as far from an excuſe for your ſo doing, as the man was who was ſpeechleſs, when it was ſaid unto him, <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou hither, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on the Wedding Garment?</hi> this will be your ſtate then; for I tell you, there is no excuſe now to be made, no pleading of Ignorance now, no ſaying (although many fooliſh ignorant people will now ſo ſay) when the Lord gives grace, or when the Lords time is come, and when the Lord pleaſe to give us power, then ſo and ſo: but take ye notice, and let it be a warning unto you, and an information; the Grace of God is given, the true Light now ſhines, by which thou mayeſt ſee, and know, and underſtand the things that belong to thy peace; and therefore ſhut not thine eyes, ſtop not thine ears, fold not thy arms and cry, Yet a little more ſleep in ſin, and in the luſts of this world, leſt God in Judgment leave thee to be paſt feeling, and thou be ſhut up, and ſealed up in utter darkneſs, where ſhall be weeping and wailing for ever more: Doth not Wiſdom cry? doth not Underſtanding utter her voice? bleſſed is the man that heareth me, watching dayly at my gates, and giving attendance at the poſts of my doors; for he that findeth me, findeth life; and ſhe is ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe that wait for her, and prevent thoſe that early ſeek her, by firſt ſhewing her ſelf unto them: ſo be not ye dull of hearing, ſhut not your eyes from beholding Wiſdoms wayes, be not careleſs in your Spirits and preſumptuous, trifling away your pretious time in a light mocking, ſcoffing Spirit, for ſuch walk after their own ungodly luſts, but learn wiſdom (which is the fear of the Lord) whilſt you may, and to redeem the time that you have miſpent; have ye a watchful careful mind and Spirit in the Lord, leaſt alſo that little time which remains unto you, be likewiſe ſpent in vain, and you paſs away ſpeedily into the pit, with the workers of iniquity, out of which there
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48168:7"/> is no Redemption; for mans life ſoon paſſeth away, it's ſaid to be ſwifter than a Weavers Shuttle, the ſwift paſſing away of which, many of you have a certain knowledge of; and ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a Poſt, that tarrieth not: and what, know you who ſhall live until to-morrow? it is ſaid, to-day, whilſt it is called to-day, the time preſent is only ours, all fleſh is graſs, and the glory of man as the flower of the field; and doth not the graſs ſoon wither, and the flower ſoon fade away? even ſuch is this preſent certain-uncertain ſtate and life of ours; but the word of the Lord (which <hi>David</hi> ſaid he hid in his heart, that he might not ſin againſt him) endures for ever; hide it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in your hearts, that ye may have it for your friend in the moſt needful time, which is at hand, and cannot, nor muſt not be delayed.</p>
            <p>And now my mind is turned (in tender love) towards you. O ye the people of Profeſſion, that make profeſſion of God and Chriſt, the holy Spirit and Scriptures of truth, O that ye were found in the poſſeſſion and inheritance of theſe things that ſo much barrenneſs of ſoul, heavineſs of Spirit, and dulneſs of ſight and hearing might not abound amongſt you as there does; for inſtead of a garden dreſſed by the hand of a skilful Husbandman, you are as a field of a Forreſt, where the hedge is broken down, and where the beaſts of the Forreſt have their repoſe; O that I could ſay of you that ye are as a watered garden, as a fruitful Land which the Lord hath bleſſed, and that his dew, dew from heaven, is diſtilled plentuouſly into your ſouls, that thereby your hearts are revived and made to leap for joy: but I ſee you like many fenced Cities laid waſte, and like a fruitful Land turned into barrenneſs, for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them that dwell therein: For, Friends, if to the Line you be brought, crookedneſs and perverſneſs doth appear, and the Ax muſt come upon you, before you will be ſquar'd for the Lords heavenly building; and when you are weighed in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48168:8"/> ballance of the Sanctuary, you are found too light; ſo that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, the hand writing upon the wall is as certainly againſt you, as it was againſt <hi>Belſhazzer,</hi> and the Kingdom will be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from you: and therefore I, your Neighbour and Friend, do counſel and adviſe you, as one who hath received great mercy and kindneſs of the Lord, to return and come from thoſe things, wherein you have exerciſed your ſelves, and have a life in, things without ſubſtance, life or virtue, unto him that ſearcheth your hearts, that ſtands at the door and knocks; why ſhould he not be let in? for he ſpeaketh on this wiſe, if any man hear my voice, and opens the door to me, I will come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and ſup with him, and he with me; and is not this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement enough to ſatisfie your ſouls, and to anſwer his deſire, in letting him in, for his preſence giveth life, and at his right hand are pleaſures for ever more: he ſhews unto man his thoughts, and makes manifeſt what is reprovable; I ſay, at the door he ſtands and knocks, open ye unto him, and in the humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of your hearts, and let not his wooings be any longer ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by you: yea, be ye open, ye everlaſting gates, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one may enter in, and diſpiſe not his lowly appearance, but ſit ye down under his ſhaddow, and his fruit will be ſweet to your taſte: come, come away from the barren Mountains, where the paſture of life is not enjoyed, and come taſte with me and many thouſands more, how good he is, and ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how lovely he is, and beautiful altogether; for I muſt tell you, that your Forms, your Ordinances and Obſervations, which you have ſet up to worſhip the Lord in, are lifeleſs ſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs things, empty and void of the Spirit of Life, yea empty ſounds and notions; ſo that your withering is ſeen, the cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherewith you cover your ſelves is not of the Spirit of the Lord, and your nakedneſs doth appear, your darkneſs is felt, in which you grope after that (namely eternal life) which you cannot attain unto therein the life is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ified, the holy one is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48168:8"/> over it all, and his cry is unto man, and unto the ſons of men, Worſhip God, give glory and honour unto his Name, who made the heavens and the earth; for he ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, and in the ſpirit and in the truth it muſt be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: therefore ceaſe ye from the works of your own hands, and ceaſe ye from the man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of? truly my Friends, not at all, I have tryed them; I have tryed them in the day of my diſtreſs, when the heart-ſercher found me out, and when he aroſe to Judgment, who pleads with all fleſh by burning and devouring fire, then my iniquity became my burthen, and my ſoul want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Saviour, and a thouſand worlds (had I had them) would I have parted with for the boſom of this beloved; I tryed firſt one, and then another, and found them ſhort of giving food to my ſoul, or Phiſitians of value, the beſt of them ſo account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of; then ſaid I unto the Lord, Lift up thou the light of thy countenance upon me; Lighten mine eyes, O Lord, leſt I ſleep the ſleep of death: and whilſt I read the Scriptures I did clearly ſee, that I was ſhort of that bleſſed life, in which the righteous obtained the Promiſes; and I a poor miſerable cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (whoſe captivity had been long and grievous) cryed out before the Lord, in diſtreſs which is unutterable, and ſaid, Surely thy love, in ſending Jeſus Chriſt into the world to ſave ſinners, is in vain as to me, for I have not the benefit thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a ſad time it was, mourning and ſorrow was as my dayly food, and in diſtreſs and grief I mourned out many of my dayes and nights before the Lord, who alone knew my ſorrow, and unto whom alone my ſoul cryed for relief, and at length he was pleaſed to ſhorten thoſe dayes, and ſatisfie my ſoul (in the dayly waiting upon him) with his goodneſs.—</p>
            <p>And now, Friends, in the holy ſence and bleſſed effect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, doth my ſoul thus labour for you, that you alſo may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to truſt alone in the Name of the Lord revealed,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48168:9"/> which is not afar off but neer you, and in you, to work your works for you, that he may deliver your ſouls from the pit, and pluck your feet out of the mire and clay, where they ſtick faſt whatever you think, and will ſtick faſt, if not unto him you anſwer whilſt he calls, who doth enlighten you; that ſo through his heavenly ſhinings into your hearts, you may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in him believe and be ſaved, with an everlaſting ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And, Friends, you pretend to Reformation, and to Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but from what, and to what? the voice and cry of the Holy One (who is going forth to ſlay with the Sword of his mouth, thoſe his enemies, that will not that he ſhould reign) is, Come out of <hi>Babylon</hi> my people, be not partaker with her in her ſins, leſt ye alſo partake with her in her Judgments; and be ye ſeparated, and touch no unclean thing (mark that word, no unclean thing) and I will be your God, and ye ſhall be my people: now is it thus with you, are you in ſuch a Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? are you thus come out from amongſt them? or in what doth your Separation and Reformation conſiſt? can you before the Lord, the Searcher of your hearts, in his holy fear anſwer yea, or are not you rather at a ſtand in your ſelves, as knowing that it is not thus with you indeed, but are drawing neer with your lips, and your hearts in the mean time far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from him; truſting in the thoughts of your own hearts, and in the Arm of fleſh, (vain man) who dawb with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Morter, who can be removed into a corner, and who to feed their own bellies, ſtarve their ſouls, keeping you from the true Biſhop and Shepherd of them; if it be not thus with you, and that whilſt you Profeſs a Separation from the world, you intend not from the evil of the world, but live in the Love and Friendſhip of the world, (which is enmity againſt God) and ſet thereby at naught him, who hath the power, and calls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you to ſeparate you by his Light and Grace in your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, Why are you ſo Conformable to this preſent evil world,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48168:9"/> as you are, in its Faſhions, Cuſtoms and Delights? and ought you not rather to be transformed by the renewing of your minds, that ye may prove what is the good will of God, and learn a bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to your tongues, (thoſe unruly members) which ſet the whole courſe of nature on fire; and ſo ſet a watch before the door of your mouths, that you may not offend in your words, but be ſlow to ſpeak, and ſwift to hear him that ſpeaks from heaven; and ſlow to ſpeak before him who ought of right to have the preheminence in all things in you: The marks of Chriſt Jeſus, do they appear in your foreheads, or his lovely-lowly ſelf-denying Image, who is meek and lowly in heart, and ſaid, My Kingdom is not of this world, if my Kingdom were of this world, then would my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants fight: Conſider well of this, leaſt yours be of this world, and that your portion be in this life.</p>
            <p>But my Friends, much might be writ and brought to your view and conſideration, but the ſum, and that which concerns you to know &amp; experience is, there ought to be a dayly watching in the light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, againſt every appearance of evil; a dayly taking up the Croſs to ſelf; a dayly dying, and a dayly mortifying; yea, and a dayly quickning, and a dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing, and a dayly growing and increaſing in the grace of God, that mortification may be known, and lived in, of the luſts and vile affections, and a being born again, and a dayly putting on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and a dayly walking not after the fleſh but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Spirit, if ſo be that ye would come to the inheritance of the Saints in Light, and to know what it is to be born again not of mortal ſeed, but of immortal; and to know that bread, &amp; to eat of it, which comes down from Heaven; and to drink of that water which they that drink of thirſt no more; for it is in ſuch as do, a well of living water, ſpringing up into everlaſting life; and ſo a conformity to his holy will you ought to witneſs, who is the ſalvation of God, prepared before the face of all people, a Light (as good old <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaid) to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to lighten their feet out of the Darkneſs, and to be the glory of his people <hi>Iſrael;</hi> who believe in his name, who walk in his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48168:10"/> Light, who paſs their ſojourning here in his fear, and in his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; whoſe converſations ſhew that they ſeek for a City whoſe maker and builder is God; theſe are they who walk in the Light of the Lord, and do not reject it, nor ſtumble at it, putting Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs; with whom the ſecrets of the Lord are, to whom he ſhews forth his Covenant, and brings to his Mercy-ſeat; feeds with his dayly bread, waters with his holy dew from above, watcheth over for good; directs by his eye, leads on by his Spirit through all temptation, perſecutions and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and finally Crowns with his Crown, his life and Glory, in the Kingdome of his Father.</p>
            <p>And therefore buy the Truth, and give all for it without grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for what is to be compared to it? neither Silver, Gold, nor pretious Stones: and conſider ye, let underſtanding have place in you, for it is ſaid, hoe every one that thirſteth come, buy Wine and Milk without Money and without Price; and who will, let him take of the water of life freely. And now remember ye the young man and his caſe, who came (it is ſaid) running to Jeſus, and ſaid, Good Maſter, What ſhall I do that I may inherit eternal Life? and Jeſus ſaid unto him, thou knoweſt the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and he anſwered, all theſe things I have obſerved from my youth, and Jeſus loved him, and ſaid, one thing is lacking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, go and ſell all that thou haſt, and come follow me, and take up the Croſs; here Jeſus came neer unto him: now here is ſomething, which may be ſaid to be, and is your caſe, as to the one thing lacking; the ſelling of all, following Jeſus, and taking up the Croſs; the want of which is the cauſe of that woful dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, worldlyneſs and ignorance that is amongſt too many of you, and hard it is to make you to believe it: but it is ſaid, that the young man who came running to Jeſus, had great Poſſeſſions, and ſo was ſad, at what was ſaid unto him, and went away ſorrowful; and ſo have you, but your Poſſeſſions and his differ much, and yet how unwilling are you to come to Jeſus, ſell all, take up the Croſs and follow him; but the man that ſold all to buy the field where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was the Pearl was a wiſe man, and well inſtructed in the things
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48168:10"/> which belonged to his eternal peace; and you ſhall do well to buy Eye-ſalve that you may ſee, and find white Rayment, that your nakedneſs may be covered, of Jeſus Chriſt whilſt he ſayeth, I counſel thee to buy of me, leſt ye remain in blindneſs and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, until no eye pitties you.</p>
            <p>And ſo this is a certain living Teſtimoy, unto the univerſal Love of God in Jeſus Chriſt, to the Souls of all men; which I counſel you to conſider of in ſecret, or in your Cloſets before the Lord, who ſearcheth the heart, that ſo your ſouls may have a place to reſt in, which is true, and in truth, and abides and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains over all imaginary, falſe, and inſecure hideing places, which now you are ſhort of, in uncertainties, doubts ſometimes, and fears, your own thoughts and vain hopes, which will prove at laſt as void and empty of ſoul ſatisfaction, and aſſurance unfail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the hour of need and great diſtreſs, which haſteth ſwiftly, upon you, as ſparks of your own kindling, which thoſe that kindle them, notwithſtanding, muſt lie down in ſorrow.</p>
            <p>And is likewiſe my ſouls deſire in the Lord, in his Love, in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and plainneſs unto you, that you truſt no longer your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Souls ſhort (or without) that great ſalvation which is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who inlightens you, that all theſe that believe in him, might not periſh, but have everlaſting life; and remember what is written, whilſt you have the light, believe in the Light, that you may become children of the light, wherein no occaſion of ſtumbling is; and I hope, as concerning ſome of you, my love herein ſhall not altogether be as water ſpilt upon the ground, which cannot be gathered up again; for is there not an honeſt heart that will conſider? a breathing ſoul that wants peace with the Lord, that will conſider? a thirſty wounded ſpirit, that wants true balm, that will conſider? or a blind man that wants his ſight, that will conſider theſe things, will ſeriouſly pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe things, to ſeek and to ſearch, that they may attain unto the truth, that will not be as the ſtony ground, where no true en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance can be had; nor as Subjects of the Prince of the Aire, from whom theſe things may flee away as the wind, which no man
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48168:11"/> knows whence it comes, nor whither it goes; ſo inconſtant and unſettled is the minds of ſuch; but rather make diligent ſearch, and ſeriouſly examine, what is here in true kindneſs ſent unto them, and offered to their due and weighty conſideration, and wherein Gods witneſs anſwers in your hearts and conſciences, to the truth, neceſſity and kindneſs thereof, ſo receive ye, ſo believe and walk; that in all things, which you put your hands unto, his heavenly, holy, immaculate appearance in you, may be by you eyed, believed in, and conſtantly obeyed, in a holy ſtedfaſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and diligence, to walk before him in the Light, as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Light, whereunto you are called, and exhorted; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til you have made your calling and election ſure, and wrought out your Salvation with fear and trembling: for know ye, that our God is a conſuming Fire, and will in no wiſe acquit the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ungodly, but render Tribulation and Anguiſh to every ſoul that doth evil.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> prayed for Wiſdom to the Lord, and was heard in that which he prayed; and in his <hi>Proverbs</hi> he thus ſaith; <hi>I paſſed by the Field of the Sloathful, and by the Vineyard of the Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of Underſtanding, and ſo it was all grown over with Thorns, and Nettles had covered the face thereof, and the Stone Wall was broken down: Then I beheld and conſidered it well, I looked upon it and received Inſtruction: Yet a little Sleep, a little Slumber, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle folding of the hands to Sleep: So thy Poverty cometh as one that Travelleth by the way, and thy Neceſſity like an Armed Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48168:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
